Hello everyone and welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine
and today we have
an upper intermediate
level lesson all about money.
That's right, we are
going to be talking
about money, but most
importantly we need to
start saving money,
we need to spend less.
Exactly, so in order to control spending,
today we're talking about budgeting.
So let's take a look at this very important
word in today's vocabulary preview.
All right, so as you mentioned,
budgeting is what is to budget?
To budget, that's the verb, so budgeting
is deciding how to spend your money.
Okay, so that means that we prepare
a plan for how to spend money.
All right, so that can
be a noun and a verb.
A budget is the plan
on how you're going to
spend money and two
budget is to execute this plan.
Exactly.
Today we're budgeting of families spending.
We're trying to control how much
this family will spend in the future.
All right, very good.
So why don't we listen to
this dialogue for the first time?
Welcome Mr. and Mrs.
Carnwell, please take a seat.
Thank you.
So I understand that
your family spending has
skyrocketed and you
want to start budgeting.
Yes, that's correct.
Hopefully speaking, our
household income is relatively
high and we have never
had any money problems.
But I think this is the main reason as to
why our spending has gone out of control.
We have two kids and
with allowances paying
their credit cards as and not to
mention our mortgage and car payments.
With the recent economic
downturn, my husband's
business has suffered
and now we need some
advice as how we can
prepare a family budget.
I see.
Well, you have come to the right place.
First, what we need to do
is determine your cash flow.
Knowing how much
money is coming in will help
us allocate spending
to different categories
such as mortgage,
education, groceries, etc.
Yes, that makes sense.
Secondly, I need you to bring all of your
receipts for the last two to three months.
That way we can
determine what your average
expenditures are and see which category
you're spending money on the most.
Usually your fixed costs are higher
and we can't do much about that.
But we can usually trim your variable
costs such as entertainment or clothing.
Great!
We will do that then.
Now, how about we
treat you to a nice dinner?
That's another thing.
If you really want to
stop spending so much
money, throw away at
least half of your credit cards.
All right, we're back.
So there were some
interesting words and
phrases in this dialogue
related to budgeting
in a lot of financial terms here, so let's
get started now on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
This first term is very
important because it
tells us what kind of a
budget we're talking about.
We're not talking about a company
here, we're talking about a family.
Right.
And so in this case we use
the phrase, "Household", okay?
So what are we talking about?
"Household" income.
All right.
Income, we know is the amount of money
that comes in to maybe your wallet, right?
My income, my personal income.
That's how much money you earn.
Okay.
So a household income is how
much money the house earns.
So all the people that are
living in this house, right?
That's right.
So it could be a
family, it could be two
married people who
are married to each other.
So the idea is that it's not one person's
income, it's the household income.
Think of a house.
All right.
It's the combined
income of everyone that's
living there or that's making
money that lives in this house.
Right.
So if Marco and I have
a household, I earn
$10,000 and here in $10,000,
our household income is $20,000.
Very good.
All right.
So then now we know that what
our household income is and in
this case we have children and
we give our kids an allowance.
Okay.
So I had an allowance when I was a kid.
This is the amount of money I
got from my parents every week.
So I get I think $10 a week and I
could spend it on anything I wanted.
And I didn't have to
work because my parents
gave the money to me and
so an allowance is this money.
It's the money that mom
and dad gave to their
children maybe every
month or maybe every week.
Now it's not only
related to children, right,
because maybe if you
have a brother or maybe
you're married and your wife is a housewife,
maybe you give her an allowance, right?
Or the opposite, maybe your house husband
and you get an allowance from your wife.
That's right.
You can have an allowance if you're anyone.
You can also have an allowance
from your company if you go traveling.
So if you have a business
trip, your company
gives you a food
allowance that the amount
of money you can spend on food
and you don't have to work for it.
That's the best part.
Awesome.
All right.
So after these allowances,
they were talking
about well how the
economic downturn has
affected their income and their spending.
Okay, so down, you think this
is a negative thing, you're right.
Down turn means when something, when a
situation gets worse, okay, or slows down.
And in this case, the
economy is what got worse
and you remember
this from last year things
started to get very difficult
for people who are in business.
And this has affected families and so we
call the situation an economic downturn.
Now the opposite would be an economic boom.
That's right, a boom is
when things are going well.
That means people are earning more money.
There are more jobs.
All right.
Very good.
And now moving on as
they were talking about
budgeting, they mentioned
this very important word.
Very technical is to allocate
money into different areas.
That's right.
Or allocate spending.
This is a verb to allocate.
That means to decide
where the money will go.
Okay, so as the mother
in a family, I will allocate
10% of the money to
the children's allowances.
That's a lot.
50% to the mortgage, 20% to the car.
Okay.
Car repairs.
So you're allocating your spending.
That's right.
I'm deciding where to spend the money.
Okay.
And while talking about spending,
we have these word expenditures.
Expenditures.
So this is a really
important word if you're in
business as well, because
we consider expenditures
when we're talking about
how much a company earns.
Expenditures are things
that we spend money on.
So remember that we're expenditures spend.
Okay.
So an expenditure.
And this is a noun.
And usually it's in the
plural expenditures.
Exactly expenditures.
So we have many expenditures at my house.
Among them, we have the car,
the rent, health care, things like that.
Okay.
Perfect.
So really good phrases there,
really good vocabulary items.
Why don't we move on
now to fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
We've got some very fun phrases
today, Marco in fluency builder.
This first one is a very common phrase that
we hear in songs and movies to skyrocket.
All right.
What is skyrocket?
Well, you think about a rocket, you
know, that's a ship that goes to space.
To skyrocket means to
go up really high, really fast.
Okay.
The price of gas has skyrocketed.
So I remember when I was a kid,
gas used to be 98 cents a gallon.
Wow.
Really.
And in the 2000s, the price skyrocketed
and it ended up being like $4 a gallon.
Yeah.
It was really expensive.
All right.
So this is also, you
can talk about sales
have skyrocketed or the price
of petroleum has skyrocketed.
Maybe a good thing or a bad thing
depending on what you're talking about.
All right.
And now moving on, they said
that their spending was out of control.
Yeah.
So this family doesn't seem
to understand how to budget.
They spend on everything.
And so the, the, the, the accountant
says that your spending is out of control.
That means that you're spending too much.
There's no order to the
way that you're spending.
All right.
And we actually have
a lesson, a previous
lesson called out of
control spending that we
also touched this topic of what
we talk about out of control.
Something is out of control.
A person can be out of control.
Like a child, this child is out of control.
He never stops screaming
and hitting people.
All right.
And our last phrase
for today, the, the
accountant says, well,
you've come to the right place.
Okay.
This is him.
This is the accountant bragging.
He's saying, well, I can fix your problems.
I can help you.
You've come to the right place.
You can use this in many different ways.
For example, um, I have
a problem, maybe with,
uh, with my TV and I
say Marco, oh my gosh.
My TV doesn't work.
I don't know what to do.
Can you help?
Right.
And I can say, well, you've
come to the right place.
I can fix your TV.
Mark goes in expert in electronics.
All right.
So you've come to the right place.
It's a very common
phrase, especially as you
say when somebody's
trying to brag and say,
well, I know how to fix your
problems or I know what you need.
I'm good at this.
You've come to the right place.
If you want to learn English,
you've come to the right place.
EnglishPod.com.
All right.
So let's listen to our
dialogue for the last time.
Welcome, Mr. and Mrs. Carnwell.
Please.
Take a seat.
Thank you.
So I understand that
your family spending has
skyrocketed and you
want to start budgeting.
Yes.
That's correct.
Frankly speaking, our household income is
relatively high and we have never had any
money problems, but
I think this is the main
reason as to why our spending
has gone out of control.
We have two kids and with
allowances paying their credit
cards as and not to mention
our mortgage and car payments.
With the recent economic
downturn, my husband's
business has suffered
and now we need some
advice as how we can
prepare a family budget.
I see.
While you have come
to the right place, first,
what we need to do is
determine your cash flow.
Having how much money
is coming in will help
us allocate spending
to different categories
such as mortgage,
education, groceries, etc.
Yes.
That makes sense.
Secondly, I need you to bring all of your
receipts for the last two to three months.
That way we can
determine what your average
expenditures are and see which category
you're spending money on the most.
Usually your fixed costs are higher and we
can do much about that, but we can usually
trim your variable costs such
as entertainment or clothing.
Great.
We will do that then.
Now how about we
treat you to a nice dinner?
That's another thing.
If you really want to
stop spending so much
money, throw away at
least half of your credit cards.
All right.
We're back.
So now talking about allowances, you said
you had an allowance when you were a kid.
Did you really have a $10 a week allowance?
No.
I think it was like eight.
It started out at $6 or $5 a week.
I think the most I got was like 10 or 11.
Oh wow.
So it was like almost about a dollar a day.
About that.
But usually the point
was that, well, I started
working when I was
15 because my parents
thought it was important for
children to learn how money works.
But I was given that
money because it's at the
time it was enough
money to go out one night.
So on Friday nights, if
I wanted to go out with
my friends, I could go out to watch
a movie and get a slice of pizza.
What $10 was enough?
Now $10 doesn't even buy
you a ticket to the movie.
But at the time, it was more than enough.
So this is important, I
guess, because different
families have different ways
of upbringing their children.
And in many cases, this
doesn't happen, right?
If I want to go out to the movies on a
Saturday, then my parents will give me $30.
And if I want to go out next
weekend, they'll also give me money.
So it's interesting to see the contrast.
Because obviously,
when I was a kid, also, I
didn't really get this opportunity
of going out of the time.
And actually, I had to work for it.
So if I wanted to go
out on the weekend, I
would get an allowance, but
also, I would have to wash the car.
That was typical with my dad.
I had to wash the car.
Well, I think it's
interesting because it shows
that the parents want
to teach their children
about budgeting, because if you only
have $10, you really have to budget.
You have to decide how you will allocate
that money, even though it's not very much.
So in some ways, it's good practice.
Yeah, it is.
I think it's done as well.
We're not in debt.
Not yet.
All right.
So let us know how allowances
work in your country, or
maybe did you have an
allowance when you were a kid?
A lot of people didn't have an allowance.
I know a lot of friends
didn't get allowances.
So come to our
website, englishpot.
com, and if you have any other questions
or doubts, please leave them there as well.
We hope to hear from you.
Until next time.
Bye, everyone.